<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Free thoughts of the penal laws, tests, and some late printed papers touching both in a letter from a person of quality.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33793</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13565892</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13565892</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100309</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40420)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100309)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1034:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Free thoughts of the penal laws, tests, and some late printed papers touching both in a letter from a person of quality.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n. ],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  England.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100309:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100309:1"/>
            <head>FREE THOUGHTS <hi>of the</hi> PENAL LAWS, TESTS, <hi>and ſome Late</hi> Printed Papers <hi>touching Both.</hi> In a Letter from a Perſon of Quality.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I HAVE carefully peruſed all your <hi>Private Reaſons,</hi> as well as the <hi>Publick Prints</hi> you ſent, to convince me of the preſent <hi>Expediency,</hi> if not <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Repealing the Penal Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Prints,</hi> I cannot but ſtand amazed to ſee ſuch inveterate Malice, and open-fac'd ſcorn, as moſt of thoſe Papers carry in them, ſo confidently walk abroad, and that <hi>ſent forth</hi> by Men of pretended Sanctity, Orthodoxy, and pure Chriſtian Zeal; for ſuch the <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters</hi> claim to be; and indeed I have known not a few of them, for the main, very exemplary in all thoſe qualities. It is prodigious to think that men ſo implacably (and upon rational grounds many of them) ſet againſt the Corruptions of <hi>Rome,</hi> men who hold it as firmly as any part of their Creed, That the Papal Power and Church is the great Antichriſt; who but as yeſterday were with one mouth exclaiming and writing againſt many of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as Apoſtates from the Doctrine of the Reformation, for otherwiſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the Propheſies touching Antichriſt; who ſince that, ſeeing the Conſtancy and Strength of the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Teſtimonies againſt Popery, have profeſſed their ſorrow for their late overcharging her Clergy as too nearly allied to <hi>Rome,</hi> and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected; who have ſome of them confeſſed the Epiſcopal Church to be the great Bulwark againſt the Power of <hi>Rome:</hi> It is prodigious, I ſay, to think that thoſe men ſhould in a moment turn tail, and with ſuch Zeal and Indignation at the poor Church of <hi>England,</hi> offer themſelves unanimouſly to join with <hi>Rome,</hi> to pull down their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken Mother; profeſſing more liking of a <hi>Publick Toleration</hi> of the juſt-now abhorred <hi>Popery,</hi> than of the Engliſh Conſtitution, and thereby <hi>verifying</hi> what they have ſo long complained was falſly and injuriouſly laid to their charge, that <hi>they were the People which would bring in Popery, if ever it came in.</hi> The incredibility that theſe men ſhould act thus, makes me, I confeſs, rather believe that theſe Papers are generally <hi>writ</hi> by ſome <hi>Crafty men</hi> (of <hi>another perſwaſion),</hi> in their Writings, if not otherwiſe alſo, <hi>perſonating Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> and that perhaps amongſt other ends, to poſſeſs the world, there is, even in the beſt ſort of the Diſſenters, more Rancor and Uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs than ever moſt of their Adverſaries conceived to be in any of them. This the <hi>A-la-mode Smartneſs of the Stile,</hi> the <hi>Reliſh of the Arguments,</hi> the <hi>want of a Senſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and the <hi>waving good Conſcience</hi> throughout the whole management, together with ſeveral Marks, (which I will not now name) in moſt of the Papers, further induce me really to believe. Upon which belief I ſhall take no further notice of them, hoping all ſober Nonconformiſts are ſenſible how abominably themſelves are wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch dealing; and if I am in an Error touching them, that they accepting my Charity, will pardon my miſtake; I chuſe to err on the beſt ſide; only this I muſt ſay of thoſe Prints which I have ſeen, Beſides Bitterneſs, and ſhameleſs Calumnies againſt the poor Church of <hi>England,</hi> there is little of moment in them for me to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, or anſwer: There is <hi>not one writ with any tolerable Temper;</hi> nor can certainly the Bleſſing of Peace, or of any tolerable good ſucceſs on their ſide, attend ſuch vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent and unpeaceable Writings; <hi>Dominus increpet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100309:2"/>
            <p>As to <hi>your private Arguments,</hi> they are (God be bleſſed) quite of another vein; and for <hi>my own particular Sentiments,</hi> I had thought you well knew much leſs Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment needed to have perſwaded me, how unmeet a Motive to Chriſtianity any kind of Compulſion is. I ever was of the mind, not only that <hi>Faith ought not</hi> to be <hi>compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> but that <hi>it cannot.</hi> You know my conſtantly avowed Maxim, <hi>It is not in mens powers to believe what they will:</hi> Penalties may make a man a Hypocrite, they can never of themſelves make him a Believer or good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Nor does it at all ſatisfie me, that ſome ſay, Men are only <hi>forced</hi> to the <hi>means of Faith,</hi> as to go to Church, to hear Sermons, and the like, but not to <hi>Faith itſelf;</hi> for beſides, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That this Plea is falſe, (to Swear, Abjure, take the Sacrament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are the moſt ſolemn kind of Profeſſions of Faith aſſignable, and not at all means to convince a man of Truth): Beſides this, I ſay, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Even to <hi>come to Church</hi> it ſelf (that is, to be preſent, and by Preſence ſeeming to be communicable in the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy) is what many judg in their Conſcience unlawful, or are not ſatisfied of the Right thereof; it is therefore contrary to their <hi>Faith,</hi> or a kind of <hi>act, profeſſing to believe what is not believed:</hi> The caſe is the ſame, if for <hi>Faith</hi> I had put <hi>Conſcience;</hi> for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as it cannot be ſuppoſed ſubject to the attempts of force, being nothing but an inward ſenſe or perſwaſion of the lawfulneſs or unlawfulneſs of Human Actions, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers little or nothing from Faith, in the acceptation wherein I have above uſed the name: And ſo in truth, neither <hi>can Conſcience be forced,</hi> tho a <hi>man</hi> may be <hi>forced</hi> to act <hi>againſt his Conſcience;</hi> which as it is a <hi>ſin</hi> of the moſt hainous nature in him <hi>who does it,</hi> ſo do I not ſee how we can excuſe him from the breach of the <hi>Law of Charity,</hi> who <hi>compels</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Nor are generally the <hi>Authors</hi> or <hi>Maintainers of Penal Laws,</hi> I ſuppoſe, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this: for all ſuch Laws allow unto men the <hi>Option of Suffering,</hi> or the <hi>choice of the Penalty,</hi> which the Law inflicts, in caſe of non-performance of its poſitive part; by which choice men may preſerve their Conſciences inviolate: And foraſmuch as there is and will be to the end of the world, different Judgments amongſt men, that is, all mens Conſciences touching the ſeveral Rites or Modes of Worſhip, and other controverted Points in Religion, will never agree: Whether therefore the <hi>Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and <hi>common Peace</hi> can be <hi>preſerved,</hi> by <hi>leaving all ſorts of men</hi> to the <hi>free exerciſe of their Conſcience,</hi> without ſome <hi>Laws to reſtrain ſome of them</hi> (which Laws if <hi>effectual</hi> to the aforeſaid Ends of Peace and Government, muſt be <hi>Penal)</hi> is the <hi>great Queſtion,</hi> upon the reſolving of which, the having or not having Penal Laws, muſt be determined.</p>
            <p>And that which <hi>encreaſeth</hi> the <hi>difficulty</hi> of <hi>reſolving</hi> this Queſtion, as ſome would have it reſolved, is, That <hi>Faith and Conſcience</hi> ſignifying things <hi>inviſible,</hi> and not to be known but by the Searcher of all hearts, it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> always to <hi>diſcern between them,</hi> and the <hi>pretences of them.</hi> Now Factious, Turbulent, and Wicked Men, tho they may be, and commonly are Atheiſts, having indeed no Faith or Conſcience, yet they never will want moſt ſpecious Pretences of both, and thoſe ſuitable and accommodate to their own ends: From whence it follows, that tho it ſhould be <hi>poſſible</hi> to <hi>preſerve Peace and Government,</hi> allowing <hi>Liberty</hi> to the Exerciſe of <hi>Conſcience truly ſo called,</hi> yet it will be utterly impoſſible to preſerve either Peace or Government, allowing Liberty to all pretences of Conſcience; for this is to allow Liberty to Faction and Villany: And by reaſon of the aforeſaid <hi>inviſibility</hi> of Conſcienee, it will be alſo <hi>impoſſible</hi> to allow <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> except we <hi>together allow</hi> Liberty to the <hi>pretences of Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence it ſeems neceſſarily concluſible, that they who will <hi>conſult</hi> the <hi>publick ſafety,</hi> and the <hi>Intereſts of Government</hi> (even <hi>abſtracted from the intereſt of Religion)</hi> muſt <hi>allow ſome reſtraint</hi> upon the exerciſe of Conſcience, and conſequently <hi>ſome ſtanding Penal Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100309:2"/>
            <p>But to take in a little the <hi>Intereſts of Religion;</hi> whether a <hi>Chriſtian Prince,</hi> allowing ſuch a <hi>qualified Liberty</hi> to the Exerciſe of Conſcience, as may conſiſt with the ſecurity of Government, ought to allow men <hi>Liberty</hi> to <hi>have no Conſcience,</hi> or to be of no <hi>Religion,</hi> or even to be of ſuch an one, as does <hi>overthrow the Common Chriſtianity,</hi> will be <hi>another Queſtion</hi> worthy of Conſideration; which yet I think every Chriſtian man will reſolve in the <hi>Negative.</hi> Diſtinctly, I mean, that tho we grant men are not to be compelled to the exerciſe of any one Religion, yet may they <hi>not be allowed</hi> openly to <hi>profeſs Atheiſm</hi> (that is, <hi>no Conſcience)</hi> nor to <hi>Blaſpheme,</hi> and in the ſame breath allow Religion to be true, and yet endeavour to ſcoff it out of the World; nor yet to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs</hi> or <hi>Practice,</hi> that is, to propagate <hi>ſuch a Religion,</hi> which is <hi>apparently inconſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>Common Chriſtianity,</hi> as <hi>Judaiſm, Mahometaniſm, Paganiſm;</hi> and if there be any other like them, as I think <hi>Muggletoniſm,</hi> and ſomewhat a kin to it.</p>
            <p>The ſum then of what we have ſaid, is this, That ſome <hi>Penal Laws</hi> ought to ſtand againſt <hi>Irreligion, Blaſphemy,</hi> and ſuch <hi>apparently ill Religions,</hi> as theſe mentioned.</p>
            <p>Again, If there be any <hi>Sect of Chriſtian</hi> Religion <hi>(at large</hi> ſo called) the <hi>Fundamental</hi> and <hi>Characteriſtical Principle</hi> of which <hi>conſiſts</hi> not with the <hi>Security of Civil Government;</hi> ſuch as I think, is the Doctrine eſſential to the Fifth-Monarchy-men, <hi>of the Reign of King Jeſus, and his Saints alone,</hi> which is alſo the Opinion of ſeveral of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and was of many of the <hi>Quakers</hi> in the year 1660. and will be ſtruck for, whenever theſe Sects are powerful enough; and how deſperately, <hi>Venner</hi> with his forty men againſt the Train'dbands of the City, and His Majeſties Life-Guard, will be an eternal Inſtance. Such Sects ought not to be allowed the free Exerciſe of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (for that, as before ſaid, is the propagating their Religion;) and therefore, againſt <hi>theſe Sects, Penal Laws ought to ſtand,</hi> at leaſt in ſome meaſure, for the reſtraint of their free Exerciſe of their Conſcience, as they will pretend, or call it: I mean for the reſtraint of their <hi>aſſembling to hold forth,</hi> and propagate theſe accurſed <hi>deſtructive Doctrines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we are come to the Point that has long pinched, and perhaps ſtill does; Whether the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>Thorow-papiſts</hi> (as ſome diſtinguiſh them) that is of thoſe, who <hi>hold the Popes full Supremacy over Princes,</hi> even within their own Dominions, be any more <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with the Security of <hi>Civil Government, generally taken,</hi> (that is, let the Prince be of what Religion he ſhall) than that of the <hi>Millenaries,</hi> or of any other like ſort; and conſequently, whether Penal Laws ought not to ſtand againſt ſuch Papiſts or Catholicks, as they will call themſelves?</p>
            <p>It ſeems to me, that thoſe of them who <hi>think their Religion</hi> well <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with Civil Government in general (be the Prince of whatſoever Chriſtian profeſſion he ſhall be, ſuppoſe a Proteſtant;) thoſe I ſay, ſhould <hi>not be againſt,</hi> or contend for the laying aſide, or not having an <hi>Oath of Supremacy, as to Temporals</hi> at leaſt; for whoſoever appears againſt ſuch an Oath, manifeſtly profeſſes thereby his Religion will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to be obedient even in Temporals, to that Governor, whoſe Supremacy in Temporals he avows he cannot, or which is the ſame, refuſes to acknowledg.</p>
            <p>It is ſure, both the Body of the <note n="*" place="margin">Diſtinct. 22. c. Omnes ſive. Ubi etiam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de gloſſam. Er Diſt. 96. Duo ſunt. Et 1. Qu. 4. Quia Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulatus.</note> 
               <hi>Canon Law</hi> aſſerts, and ſome <note n="†" place="margin">Nicolaus, Gelaſius, Leo IV. ubi ſupra, aliique</note> 
               <hi>Popes</hi> have <hi>expreſly decreed the Supremacy of the Chair</hi> of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> even in <hi>Temporals,</hi> to be of <hi>Divine right</hi> and <hi>matter of Faith;</hi> ſo as that <hi>to believe the Contrary is Hereſy and damnable Sin.</hi> And whatever ſome do believe or declare, (as I have heard ſome of them ſwear, that ſhould their Father Confeſſor, or the Pope himſelf, command them to take Arms againſt their King, they would not obey;) yet it is alſo ſure, that many <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, and perhaps more Orders of their Religious than one, do to this day ſo believe; and tho many of their Confeſſers may not preſs the Popes Supremacy in Temporals on the Conſciences of their Devotes, yet no doubt others, except they are for ſworn, do it.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100309:3"/> Further, the ſaid <note n="*" place="margin">XV Qu 6. c. Alius item. Et c. Nos San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum. Et c, Jurator milites</note> 
               <hi>Canon Law</hi> allows the Pope may <hi>Abſolve Subjects and Soldiers</hi> from their <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> and <hi>Duty</hi> to their <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Commanders;</hi> and ſeveral <note n="†" place="margin">Gelaſius, Zacharias, Gregor. VII. Urbanus II. locis proximè jam citatis, alii<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</note> 
               <hi>Popes</hi> have decreed as much, otherwiſe it could not have come into the Body of the Canon Law; nay, they have actually done it. Wherefore it would ſeem, tho not for Religions ſake in general, yet <hi>for the ſake of Civil Government, Penal Laws ought to ſtand againſt ſuch a ſtrain of Religion</hi> alſo; at leaſt, againſt the free Exerciſe of it. Whether this will conclude <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and thoſe whom ſome call <hi>Jeſuited Popiſts,</hi> themſelves beſt know; I will not now inſiſt on their <hi>fourth Vow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reſult of all is, that an <hi>abſolute Repeal of all Penal Laws</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> or even of ſuch Penal Laws which affect either <hi>Catholicks,</hi> or <hi>pretended Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters,</hi> taking Catholicks and Diſſenters for all that call themſelves ſo, is <hi>not ſafe for the Government, nor agreeable to Chriſtian Conſcience;</hi> but a <hi>Qualification of ſuch Laws,</hi> or ſome <hi>explanatory and mitigative Act,</hi> which might <hi>ſecure all peaceable conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious</hi> men of <hi>whatſoever Perſwaſion</hi> (thoſe Antichriſtian and Turbulent ones before mentioned, being excepted) in their <hi>Eſtates, Lives and Liberties,</hi> while they <hi>Worſhip God according to their Conſcience,</hi> were <hi>to be deſired,</hi> and is to be <hi>endeavoured</hi> by all who would approve themſelves genuinely <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And I am not without hopes, that thoſe who declare themſelves ſo much for the Repeal of the Penal Laws, will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg this to be their Senſe.</p>
            <p>But as I have hitherto endeavoured to be <hi>in general,</hi> juſt both to the <hi>King, Religion, and all Parties</hi> concern'd in my impartial conſidering and ſtating the caſe of all, in reference to the Liberty deſired; So I muſt be yet more <hi>in particular</hi> juſt to thoſe who are in <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> of an <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> by Virtue of the Laws; and conſider while they concede ſo much, what is fit to be conceded and aſſured to them by the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Parties.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, Seeing it is <hi>expected</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that ſhe <hi>conſent</hi> to the <hi>Repealing</hi> all ſuch Penal Laws which affect the Eſtates, Lives or Liberties of ſuch <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Catholicks and Diſſenters as before ſpecified; therefore it muſt needs be judged but <hi>fit</hi> and <hi>equal,</hi> that the <hi>Church of</hi> Rome <hi>revoke</hi> all <hi>ſuch Laws,</hi> which alike affect all <hi>peaceable Proteſtants.</hi> Thoſe who pretend that Church has none ſuch, may be excuſed if they ſpeak it out of Ignorance; but they are unpardonable who go about to impoſe ſo impudent a falſhood upon the World. The <hi>Church of Rome</hi> has for many Ages not only had <hi>Sanguinary</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> but alſo <hi>bound,</hi> and daily does bind <hi>by the moſt ſacred Oaths,</hi> and under the ſevereſt Penalties, moſt of her Sons, Sacred as well as Secular, to the <hi>Execution</hi> of ſuch Laws, to their utmoſt Power; Behold ſome of thoſe Laws, and the legal Method to be proceeded in againſt all, who own not the Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>We Excommunicate and Anathematize every Hereſy which ſets up it ſelf againſt this <note n="*" place="margin">Of which Faith, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the firſt Canon of the <hi>Lateran Council,</hi> out of whoſe Decree this Chapter is tranſcribed into the Body of the Canon Law (the Chapter being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the third Canon of the ſaid <hi>Lateran</hi> Council under <hi>Innocent</hi> III.) of which Faith, I ſay, two Points amongſt others were <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and <hi>that there is no Salvation out of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </note> holy Faith which we have above expounded, condemning all and ſingular Hereticks, by what Names ſoever they are reckoned, having indeed their Faces dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ways, but their Tails tied together, becauſe as to matter of falſhood they agree in the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>And being thus condemned, let them be left to the preſent Secular Power, and to their Bailiffs to be puniſhed <note n="†" place="margin">Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione debita.</note> with due Severity or Execution; Clergy-men being firſt degraded from their Orders, ſo that the Goods of ſuch condemned Perſons, if
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100309:3"/> they be Lay-men, be confiſcate; but if Clergy-men; be applied to the Churches whence they received Stipends.</p>
               <p>And as to thoſe who ſhall be found <note n="*" place="margin">Solâ ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one notabiles.</note> challengeable only by Suſpicion, except ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of the Suſpicion, and quality of the Perſon, they ſhall clear their Innocency by a proportionable purgation, let them alſo be ſtruck with the Sword of Excommunication [or, of an <hi>Anathema]</hi> and let them be avoided by all Perſons till they give condign Satisfaction: So that if they continue excommunicate one whole year, they be from thenceforth condemned as Hereticks.</p>
               <p>Further, Let the <hi>Secular Powers</hi> of <hi>whatſoever degree</hi> be <hi>admoniſhed</hi> and <hi>induced,</hi> and if need be, <hi>compelled</hi> by <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures,</hi> that even as they deſire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and accounted faithful, ſo they take publickly an Oath for the defence of the Faith, that they will endeavour <note n="†" place="margin">Bona fidê.</note> faithfully [or in good earneſt] according to their power, to <hi>exterminate out of the Lands of their Juriſdiction</hi> all ſuch as are pronounced <hi>Hereticks</hi> by the Church: So that from henceforth, <hi>whenſoever any one ſhall be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into Power Spiritual or Temporal,</hi> he be <hi>bound firmly to ſwear to this Article.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in caſe any <hi>Temporal Lord,</hi> being required and admoniſhed by the Church, <hi>ſhall neglect</hi> to purge his Countrey from Heretical Pravity, let him be by the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan and Comprovincial Biſhop <hi>innodated</hi> in the bond of <hi>Excommunication.</hi> And if he ſhall neglect to ſatisfy within a year, let them ſignify the ſame to the Pope, that he, from that time forth, may <hi>pronounce his Subjects abſolved</hi> from their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and may <note n="*" place="margin">Terram ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponat Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis occupen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dam.</note> 
                  <hi>ſet forth his Country</hi> to be <hi>ſeized by Catholicks,</hi> who, having exterminated the Hereticks thence, may poſſeſs it without contradiction, and keep it in the purity of the Faith, with a ſaving to the right of the principal Lord: provided <hi>he have put no obſtacle</hi> in this matter, nor given <hi>any other hindrance:</hi> The ſame Law nevertheleſs being obſerved as to them who have no Principal Lords.</p>
               <p>Further, Let all Catholicks, who, having taken upon them the badge of the Croſs, ſhall have applied themſelves to the exterminating Hereticks, injoy the ſame Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and be poſſeſſed of the ſame Privileges as have been granted to them who went to ſuccour the Holy Land.</p>
               <p>Moreover we decree, That all <hi>Adherers, Receivers, Defenders and Cheriſhers of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> lie under the <hi>ſame Excommunication;</hi> firmly ordaining, that after any ſuch <hi>Excommunicate Perſon</hi> ſhall have, one whole year, neglected to make ſatisfaction, he from that time become <hi>in Law infamous,</hi> and be not <hi>admitted to any publick Office, Councils,</hi> nor to <hi>chuſe any others,</hi> nor ſo much as to <hi>give his Teſtimony</hi> in any Caſe; that he alſo be <hi>inteſtable</hi> [or have no liberty or power to make a Will] nor be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">None of our late Teſts match the Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verity of this Law.</note> to <hi>come in ſucceſſion</hi> to any <hi>Inheritance.</hi> Furthermore, that <hi>none be compelled to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him</hi> in any <hi>Suit</hi> or Buſineſs, but that <hi>he be compelled to anſwer all</hi> others. And in caſe perchance he ſhould <hi>formerly</hi> have been a <hi>Judge,</hi> his <hi>Sentence ſhall have no ſtrength,</hi> nor ſhall any <hi>Cauſes</hi> be brought to his <hi>Audience.</hi> Or if he were an <hi>Advocate,</hi> his <hi>Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> ſhall be <hi>no-wiſe admitted.</hi> If a Publick <hi>Notary, all Inſtruments</hi> made by him ſhall be of <hi>no force,</hi> but <hi>damn'd with their Author:</hi> The ſame alſo we command to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in like caſes. If he be a <hi>Clergy-man,</hi> let him be <hi>depoſed</hi> from all <hi>Office and Benefice.</hi> And if any ſhall not forbear to avoid ſuch Perſons, after they have been pronounced Excommunicate by the Church, let them alſo by Excommunication be compelled to fit ſatisfaction. Further, let <hi>no Clerk adminiſter the Church Sacraments to ſuch Peſtilent Perſons,</hi> let them not preſume to give them <hi>Chriſtian Burial,</hi> nor let them partake of any <hi>Alms or Oblations:</hi> or in caſe they ſhall, let them [that is, ſuch Clerks ſo offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing] be deprived of their Office; to which let them never be reſtored, without a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Indulgence from the Apoſtolical See. In like manner, let all <hi>Regulars</hi> obſerve ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100309:4"/> to do: upon whom, otherwiſe, let this Penalty reſt, that their Privileges be vold within that Dioceſe wherein they have preſumed to commit ſuch Exceſſes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Thus far the <hi>Lateran Council</hi> (under Pope <hi>Innocent the Third, An. Dom.</hi> 1215.) tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed into the <note n="†" place="margin">Extra. De Haereticis Cap. Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus itaque, &amp;c.</note> body of the Canon Law; which, with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is above all other [at leaſt Humane] Laws, and it were to be wiſhed, that it were not too often obſerved above God's Law alſo.</p>
            <p>But though the Council ſtopt here; after another ſhort Chapter the Decretals go on again thus under <hi>Gregory</hi> IX. <note n="*" place="margin">Cap Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municamas, &amp;c.</note> 
               <q rend="inline">We Excommunicate and Anathematize all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, the <hi>Cathari</hi> [or Puritans] the <hi>Patarens,</hi> the Poor of <hi>Lions</hi> [and others there mentioned, now perhaps unknown] and all others, by whatſoever names they are reckoned, having Faces looking different ways, <hi>&amp;c. as before.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Being thus condemned, let them be left to the Secular Judgment to be puniſhed with due ſeverity, <hi>&amp;c. as before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if any of the aforementioned Heretics, after they are convicted, will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to perform condign Penance, let them be kept <hi>in perpetual impriſonment.</hi> And as to them who adhere to their Errors, we adjudge them alike Heretics.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The next Chapter is ſhort, but Subſtantial. <q rend="inline">Let them know that they are abſolved <note place="margin">Cap. Abſolutos ſe noverint.</note> from all Debt of Fidelity, Dominion, or Obedience, whoſoever were bound by any Compact, howſoever ſtrong, to any Perſons fallen into Hereſie.</q>
            </p>
            <p>More of like nature might be eaſily collected out of the body of the Canon-Law. Now that by <hi>Heretics</hi> thoſe Laws do <hi>not underſtand</hi> meerly <hi>Manichees, Valentinians, Arrians,</hi> or ſome ſuch groſs People, but univerſally <hi>all ſuch who ſubmit not to the</hi> Roman <hi>Faith,</hi> or even to the <hi>Supremacy of the</hi> Roman <hi>Biſhop,</hi> is, beſides what was above-noted, plain from another Text of the ſaid Canon Law. <q rend="inline">He [that is Chriſt alone] hath founded this [the <hi>Roman]</hi> Church upon a Rock, who committed to bleſſed <hi>Peter,</hi> the Keeper <note place="margin">Diſtinct. XXII Omnes.</note> of the Keys of Eternal Life, the Rights both of the Earthly and Heavenly Empire—So that whoſoever endeavours to take away from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church the Privilege given her by the Supreme Head of all Churches, ſuch Perſon without doubt is fallen into Hereſie; and whereas others [who violate the Privileges of other Churches] are to be called unjuſt, ſuch Perſon is to be ſtiled an Heretic.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As to <hi>matter of fact,</hi> how theſe Laws have been Executed, and in ſome Countries how they ſtill are, is diſagreeable to my Deſign of publick accord to inſiſt: only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are conſidering of terms of accord, I muſt not wave that point of matter of fact, that <hi>all Proteſtants are excommunicated afreſh</hi> by the <hi>Pope every Maundy Thurſday,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bulla Caenae.</note> and that every Prelate, which is conſecrated, at his Conſecration, amongſt other things, ſevere enough againſt us, ſwears in theſe words, <hi>Hereticos, Schiſmaticos &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vide Pontiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. Roman.</note> 
               <hi>eidem Domino noſtro vel Succeſſoribus pr aedictis, pro poſſe, perſequar &amp; impugnabo.</hi> That is, <q rend="inline">I will, according to my power, perſecute and impugn all Hereticks, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, or thoſe who rebel againſt our Lord [the Pope] and his Succeſſors aforeſaid.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I will not here meddle with the Doctrine of many <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> who tell us ordinarily, that all Heretics being <hi>de jure</hi> Excommunicate, any Catholic may ſafely kill them; Nor that in all Catholic Kingdoms <hi>de Conſuetudins,</hi> Burning alive is the proper Legal Death for Heretics: for which laſt, it were to be wiſht, there were not yet Statute-Laws in force, in ſome of his Majeſty's Dominions. I rub not, I ſay, on theſe Sores, but content my ſelf to have mentioned the general Penal Laws above recited, which are ſufficient to prove the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have ſuch Laws.</p>
            <p>And <hi>theſe</hi> being the <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> the preſent <hi>obligation</hi> generally to <hi>all Catholics in power</hi> (whether Eccleſiaſtical or Secular) to obſerve them, it is reaſonable, that <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Fenal Laws</hi> againſt all men of <hi>this Religion</hi> be <hi>Repealed, they of the Religion</hi> obtain
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100309:4"/> from his Holineſs ſome <hi>Repeal</hi> of <hi>theſe and the like Laws;</hi> at leaſt a <hi>Bull, exempting all the Proteſtants of</hi> England, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, from being comprehended in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſuch <hi>Heretics,</hi> who are thus to ſuffer; and together <hi>abſolving</hi> all Perſons, who have taken <hi>Oaths</hi> for <hi>Exterminating Heretics,</hi> from any obligation to perform thoſe Oaths as to the Proteſtants of theſe Countries; For till then, we have juſt ſo much Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to hope for ſecurity from ſuch Catholics, as we have aſſurance that they will ever forſwear themſelves, or all their days live in wilful Perjury.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>another Law</hi> amongſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholics, which tho not Penal to us, it is to be feared may be one day moſt dreadfully Penal to as many of them as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, and which ſeems to oblige them to perſecute us: I will call it the <hi>Law of uncharitableneſs,</hi> the revoking of which alſo, it ſeems fit, ſhould be made a condition of Repealing our Penal Laws: The Law I mean is that, whereby every one, who will be of that Church, is required to ſwear to the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Creed, in the cloſe of which Oath he avows, <hi>No one can be ſaved out of the belief of that the preſent</hi> Roman <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Faith.</hi> By this they plainly damn four fifth parts of all Chriſtendom. I know there are ſome Gentlemen of that Communion, who are more merciful to us, and the better Catholicks are they for it; God bleſs them, and encreaſe the number of them: But I as well know, there are others ſo ſtifly hold to this, that they frequently, and even in their ordinary converſation, as well as in their writings, uſe it as an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to perſwade men of our Church to come over to their Religion. As to theſe, I crave leave to ſay only this one thing, That men can repoſe very little confidence in their kindneſs, who prejudging to God's judgment, have already damn'd them before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand: Wherefore I conceive they who would have any kind offices paſs between us and our <hi>Roman</hi> Catholic Countreymen, or intend we ſhould live together as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ought to abandon this rigour, and if poſſible to procure from the Head of their Church an abatement of it, as to the Proteſtants of theſe Countries at leaſtwiſe.</p>
            <p>This will appear yet the more reaſonable, if we conſider of <hi>what Communion</hi> they were that firſt <hi>introduced</hi> into theſe parts of the World <hi>Penal or Sanguinary Laws</hi> in cauſe of Religion. The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in this matter can only be blamed for <hi>following an ill Example,</hi> which alſo they have induſtriouſly not come up to. They found Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Laws; and the ſevereſt of them, in <hi>England,</hi> they have repealed: If any other than thoſe Penal-Laws were made, (as it is not to be denied there were) it was rather upon the ſcore of the <hi>State,</hi> than of <hi>Religion.</hi> A <hi>Sanguinary Law</hi> made particularly <hi>againſt any ſort of our Non-Conformiſts,</hi> I never yet knew any: Nor againſt thoſe of <hi>Rome purely</hi> for <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſake. But the Laws above mentioned out of the <hi>Roman</hi> Canon-Law are Purely upon the ſcore of Conſcience; and even where they extend not to Blood, they are, as we ſee, much ſeverer than any of our Laws or Teſts againſt them. In a word all perſons who will be juſt, muſt allow to others the Liberty and Security that they deſire ſhould be granted to themſelves, which is the <hi>Heighth</hi> of this our <hi>firſt demand. I prae, ſequar:</hi> Let thoſe who were firſt in the guilt, firſt amend; certainly Proteſtants will meet them in kindneſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Inaſmuch as they of the <hi>Eſtabliſht Church</hi> do not in the leaſt <hi>ſuſpect the truth of their Religion</hi> (all the Writings of their <hi>Roman</hi> Adverſaries diſcovering their <hi>Roman</hi> Faith, where differing from the Proteſtants, inſtead of a Rock, to be built only on Air) and inaſmuch as it cannot be juſtly expected, that meerly to gratify our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, we ſhould at once <hi>betray</hi> both <hi>our Religion</hi> and <hi>our Intereſt;</hi> it is but <hi>juſt,</hi> that <hi>together</hi> with ſuch <hi>Statute</hi> as ſhall <hi>take away the Penal Laws</hi> in Conteſt, there paſs ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for <hi>ſecurity of the National Religion,</hi> that it ſhall not be <hi>altered;</hi> and of the <hi>regular conformable Clergy</hi> and <hi>their Succeſſors,</hi> that their <hi>Rights</hi> ſhall not be <hi>invaded.</hi> It is told us indeed, we have His <hi>Majeſties Royal word</hi> many times <hi>repeated.</hi> I humbly return,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100309:5"/> that I know no <hi>true Church-of-</hi>England-<hi>Man</hi> who does not <hi>rely</hi> upon His Majeſties Word, during his Reign (which God long continue) for the ſecurity of our Church. But <hi>Succeſſion is a long Train;</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> if ſtanding, may keep <hi>poſterity in peace,</hi> when <hi>Promiſes</hi> with their <hi>Authors</hi> are <hi>faln aſleep.</hi> He is not juſt to the preſent Age, who is not to his power juſt to Poſterity, however remote. It is therefore reaſonable, fit and neceſſary that ſuch a Statute, as is deſired, paſs.</p>
            <p>As to what you conclude with, That the <hi>Clergy of the Church of</hi> England are very <hi>ungrateful</hi> to His Majeſty for his repeated Promiſes of Protection, and together <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil</hi> to him, in not <hi>fully acquieſcing</hi> in his Royal word ſo often given for the ſecurity of their Religion, Rights and Privileges; and <hi>not offering to concur,</hi> according to his deſire, in the Repeal of the Penal Laws: I take the liberty to <hi>aver,</hi> that I know not <hi>one Clergy-man</hi> of that Church who has not <hi>ſolemnly under his hand given</hi> His Majeſty <hi>thanks</hi> for thoſe Promiſes. All the <hi>Addreſſes</hi> we made in the year of His Majeſties ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to the Crown, were ſo many <hi>humble Teſtimonies of our Gratitude,</hi> and <hi>Zealous Vows of our Loyalty;</hi> and if <hi>Addreſſes of meer Thanks, and Vows of Loyalty</hi> would be accepted, there is not an Engliſh Biſhop, Prieſt, or Pariſh in the Three Kingdoms, I believe, but would preſent them moſt gladly. But who ſees not the <hi>Declaration,</hi> for which 'tis expected we return Thanks, conſiſts of <hi>more parts</hi> than that <hi>private Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> can <hi>juſtify</hi> their approbation of the whole? And as to the ſacred Veneration we have for His Majeſties word, I have ſpoken already.</p>
            <p>Give me leave for a Concluſion to tell you a <hi>new</hi> and very <hi>true Story.</hi> A Friend and Neighbour of mine, being very intimate with an eminent perſon of a certain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Order, and knowing well the Principles of that Order, asked him in a good hour, what they meant by this furious driving on an Univerſal and Unlimited Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? The anſwer he received was, that they were now <hi>Scaffolding.</hi> My Friend under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding him not, deſired he would explain himſelf; but could get no more out of him than this, that they were <hi>yet but Scaffolding.</hi> After further importunity for a more expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit reſolution, the good Religious perſon anſwered, he would not tell him more; but bid him go to ſuch a perſon (a Maſter-Bricklayer, or Maſon, be-like) and ask him what <hi>Scaffolding</hi> was? He went to the Man aſſigned, and received this Anſwer, <hi>Scaffolding</hi> is <hi>ſetting up Poles,</hi> and <hi>Boards,</hi> and ſuch <hi>rough ſtuff,</hi> which <hi>ſerve</hi> us to <hi>build,</hi> and when we have built, we <hi>throw them aſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Story I avow to be true, and leave the application of it to all thoſe parties whom it concerns; very well remembring, that <hi>Scaffolds</hi> are <hi>ordinarily made</hi> for <hi>more uſes than one:</hi> However according to the Interpretation given, the Toleration now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted ſeems not by its Agitators deſigned to ſtand long.</p>
            <p>But to make an end: On what terms, I conceive the Penal-Laws in queſtion may be Repealed with juſtice to the preſent and ſucceeding Ages, you may eaſily collect out of this long and haſty ſcribble; and ſo you have my <hi>Free Thoughts</hi> in this ſo hotly agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated Queſtion. God preſerve the King, and grant we may live to ſee the days, wherein <hi>all Laws Penal</hi> to <hi>Peaceable, Conſcientious</hi> men, and together all <hi>uncharitable Laws,</hi> on <hi>all ſides,</hi> may be for ever abrogated.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am your Humble Servant</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed in the Year 1688.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100309:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100309:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100309:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100309:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100309:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100309:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100309:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100309:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100309:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
